Mss.B.L493
American Philosophical Society
John L. (John Lawrence) LeConte papers, 1812-1897
Mss.B.L493
American Philosophical Society
7.7 Linear feet Ca. 1900 items
This collection contains mostly entomological material, with much information on the description and identification of particular insects, entomological collections, and the study of entomology in Europe and the United States. In addition, there are materials on medicine and hospitals during the American Civil War, on the Corps of Topographical Engineers, the United States Army, on natural history in the United States, and on the LeConte's family. Some letters are written to President Rutherford B. Hayes and concern the Commissionership of Agriculture, for which LeConte was considered, but not appointed. Letters of John Eatton LeConte and Joseph LeConte are included.
Ca. 1900 items.
LeConte, John L., (John Lawrence), 1825-1883
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased from Moore ($750.00) and accessioned, 09/12/1962 (1962 1530ms). See in-house shelf list for additional sources and accession numbers and dates.
Existence and Location of Copies note
This collection is also available on microfilm (Film 1306).
Biographical/Historical note
John Lawrence LeConte (1825-1883, APS 1853), entomologist was an active member of the American Philosophical Society and founding member of the American Entomological Society; a charter member of the National Academy of Sciences in 1863; surgeon and medical inspector for the U.S. Army medical corps, 1861-1865; president of the American Association for the Advancement of Science in 1874; and Chief Clerk of the U.S. Mint in Philadelphia in 1878.
John Lawrence LeConte was the son of John Eatton LeConte (1784-1860, APS 1851) an army topographer and noted naturalist, and his wife Mary Ann Hampton. John Lawrence decided at an early age to follow in his father’s footsteps, and began collecting natural specimens, showing a particular interest in insects, especially beetles. He matriculated at Mount St. Mary’s College in Emmitsburg, Maryland, graduating in 1842. Three years later he enrolled at the College of Physicians and Surgeons in New York and received a medical degree in 1846. While a medical student, LeConte also worked as an assistant to New York botanist and chemist John Torrey (1796-1873, APS 1835). Like other contemporary naturalists who were educated as doctors, including Asa Gray (1819-1888, APS 1848), LeConte seems never to have had any intention of practicing medicine. Already in 1844 he had published a paper, describing twenty-nine species of ground beetles. From 1844 to 1846 he collected specimens in the Rocky Mountains and around Lake Superior. When the noted Swiss naturalist Louis Agassiz (1807-1873, APS 1843) explored the Great Lakes area in 1848, LeConte accompanied him. In 1849, he took another trip westward, this time traveling as far as California, returning to New York in 1851.
In 1852, LeConte and his father moved to Philadelphia, whose Academy of Natural Sciences helped to make it a center of activity for the study of natural history, including entomology. Unlike his Georgia cousin Joseph LeConte (1823-1901, APS 1873), with whom John had traveled, collected specimens, and even attended medical school, he did not enter Harvard’s new Lawrence Scientific School that opened in 1847. One reason was that Agassiz, the school’s founder and premier faculty member, had no special interest in entomology. In fact, except for the work of Frederick V. Melsheimer and Thomas Say (1787-1834, APS 1817) in the first quarter of the nineteenth century, American naturalists had described and classified few insects, routinely sending specimens abroad for identification as late as the mid-1840’s. For this reason LeConte aimed to make entomology a major field of study in the United States, focusing on the order Coleoptera (beetles), which lacked an effective taxonomy. With this goal in mind, LeConte traveled widely to collect specimens, including trips to Central America and Europe. He built a extensive collection of beetles, and also published descriptions of a number of new species. LeConte was also active in scientific organizations, participating in the affairs of Philadelphia’s Academy of Natural Sciences and the American Philosophical Society. He was a founding member of the American Entomological Society and elected an honorary member of several European scientific organizations.
1861 was a momentous year for LeConte. He began work on a monograph dedicated to the classification of the Coleoptera. He also married Helen S. Grier, the daughter of U.S. Supreme Court Justice Robert C. Grier (1794-1870, APS 1848). The advent of the Civil War disrupted his scientific work and his family life. He watched in horror as his Georgia relatives joined the secessionist cause. Soon after the War began, he volunteered to serve in the U.S. Army's medical corps, first as a surgeon and later as a medical inspector. Only in 1865 was he discharged and allowed to resume his study of natural history. Two years later in 1867 LeConte joined a railroad surveying team as a geologist and zoologist. This afforded him an opportunity to study the landforms and fauna of the Great Plains and the Rocky Mountains.
During the Civil War and the years that followed, LeConte enhanced his scientific stature by participation in nationally renown scientific bodies. In 1863 he became a charter member of the National Academy of Sciences. In 1874 he served as president of the American Association for the Advancement of Science.
LeConte published two important monographs in entomology with the assistance of George Henry Horn (1840-1897, APS 1869). The first in 1876 was on the weevils or Rhynchophora of North America. In 1883 he finished his taxonomy of the Coleoptera of North America, begun in 1861. This 600-page work classified about 11,000 different beetles. Although LeConte contributed to other fields of natural history with dozens of articles on topics in geology, paleontology and ornithology, he devoted his greatest attention to the description and classification of beetles. His published studies of the distribution of insects in the American West also helped to promote zoogeography as a means of biological inquiry.
LeConte wrote studies of insect damage to crops, and in 1877 unsuccessfully sought appointment as the U.S. Commissioner of Agriculture. Despite endorsements by fellow scientists, this office eluded him. However, President Rutherford B. Hayes later appointed him the chief clerk of the U.S. Mint in Philadelphia.
John Lawrence LeConte died in his Philadelphia home on November 15, 1883 at the age of 68, after suffering a stroke. He was the father of three children, one of whom died in infancy. His contributions to entomology, in particular his taxonomy of beetles, greatly advanced descriptive and systematic entomology. Fellow entomologist Samuel H. Scudder wrote of him in 1884, “LeConte was the greatest entomologist this country has yet produced.”
Arrangement note
Originally L493.1, L493.2, L493.3, L493.4, and L493f.
Scope and Contents Note
The LeConte papers are comprised primarily of the correspondence of John Eatton LeConte (1784-1860) and his son John Lawrence LeConte (1825-1883). Many items date 1840s and 1850s, when both father and son were active in scientific pursuits. The earliest section of papers relates to the work of John Eatton LeConte for the United States Army Corps of Topographical Engineers, with special reference to surveys of harbors of the eastern United States. The other major section of John Eatton LeConte’s letters relates to natural history, especially scholarly contributions in zoology and botany.
Widely known for his entomological research, John Eatton LeConte published forty papers in the Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia and collaborated with the distinguished French entomologist J.A. Boisduval on a natural history of butterflies and caterpillars. The largest number of letters in the collection are addressed to John Lawrence LeConte, mostly on entomological matters, with much information on the description and identification of particular insects, entomological collections, and the study of entomology in Europe and the United States. In addition, there are materials on medicine and hospitals during the American Civil War and on LeConte's family life. Some letters are written to President Rutherford B. Hayes and concern the Commissionership of Agriculture, for which LeConte was considered, but not appointed. The Family Series principally consists of letters from John Eatton LeConte, John Lawrence LeConte, Joseph LeConte, and Mrs. Jane LeConte Harden to Mrs. Matilda Jane Harden Stevens, Sumner Morrison Ramsey, Mrs. Ann LeConte Stevens, and Louis LeConte pertaining to family matters and natural history.
Correspondents of John Eatton LeConte include General Alexander Macomb, Pierre François Marie Auguste (Comte) Dejean, Thaddeus William Harris, and Frederick William Hope. John Lawrence LeConte’s correspondents include Samuel S. Haldeman, Hermann R. Schaum, Louis Agassiz, Spencer Fullerton Baird, Joseph Henry, James D. Dana, George H. Horn, Benjamin Dann Walsh. Major General Macomb, a fellow member of the Army Corps of Engineers, a hero of the War of 1812 and winner of Congressional Medal of Honor, was one of John Eatton LeConte’s primary military correspondents. He received and relayed LeConte’s proposal to Secretary of War Calhoun to explore the new territory of Florida, as well as the “Special Order” (February 1, 1822) authorized by General Winfield Scott to equip the expedition. Macomb also granted LeConte’s 1824 request for leave to recover from ill health, a condition that eventually forced his resignation from the Army in August, 1831. A December 24, 1841 letter from British naturalist Frederick William Hope suggests that LeConte eventually recovered, since he Hope feels gratified “to find that your health is reestablished.”
Over at least a ten-year period (from May, 5, 1825-April 11, 1835) LeConte traded lists of specimens in correspondence with the expatriot Napoleonic General, the Comte Dejean, who amassed and cataloged a collection of 13,000 species of birds and insects during his travels through the Balkans. LeConte also corresponded with fellow American entomologist Thaddeus William Harris, who in an April 11, 1838 inquired about the 3rd edition of Dejean’s catalogue. Finally, there are seven letters between April 10, 1829-June 9, 1833 from the French entomologist Jean Alphonse Boisduval, with whom LeConte collaborated on the 1837 Histoire général et iconographie des lepidoptérès et des chenilles de l’Amerique septentrionale.
John Lawrence LeConte also corresponded with contemporary entomologists, American and foreign. An early and frequent correspondent with John Lawrence LeConte was Samuel Stehman Haldeman, the Lancaster county, Pennsylvania entomologist and philologist. Although twelve years senior to John Lawrence LeConte, Haldeman and LeConte were close friends and lifelong correspondents. Both were pioneers in the “professionalization” of the field of entomology—Haldeman was a moving force behind the Entomological Society of Pennsylvania in 1842 and LeConte was a founding member of the American Entomological Society in 1859. A December 3, 1847 letter from Haldeman to LeConte states that he isn’t sure when their entomological society will meet again, but he is glad that they have attracted the attention of such a distinguished entomologist as the German Hermann Schaum, and that Harvard’s Louis Agassiz was also taking an interest in “their doings”.
LeConte and Haldeman regularly exchanged and discussed insect specimens, as when on March 18, 1848, the latter asked his younger friend to tell him about the “furry thing” from Santa Fe, since he hopes “to match it with an insect that lives on the surface in the mid-ocean.” On July 18, 1849 Haldeman wrote reporting that he had been describing a few hymenoptera (species of bees or wasps), and that he had just published a short history of the genus Orthopterous (crickets). Although he usually wrote to LeConte from his home in Columbia, Pennsylvania, Haldeman also occasionally corresponded from the field, as he did from Selma, Alabama, on June 1, 1852. In the letter he reports that “I have seen several new ants (at least new to me), this locality being full of them. No shells yet. Waters too high.”
After the late 1840s, when Haldeman began having trouble with his eye-sight, the substance of their correspondence changes, shifting increasingly to philological and phonological topics. A June 10, 1858 letter from Haldeman announces that at least some of his insect collection is for sale: “My collection of Coleoptera I believe to be cheap at $250, including the cabinet-but I know not the number of species, not having the catalogue here.” Afterward, the number of letters from Haldeman to LeConte decreases, although not in warmth. On March 26, 1867, when LeConte was about to travel west on a Union Pacific Railway survey, Haldeman says “I am heartily glad that you are going, but your concisity has merely whett my curiosity. For example, you have not told me (as the grammars say) how ‘much-or-many-more-most’ are going, & who’s to take care of the bugs-& for how long?”
Already by 1848 at the age of twenty-three the young John Lawrence LeConte, who had earned his medical degree just two years earlier, was an active entomologist respected in the field. This is evident from his correspondence with major American scientists of the era. For example, a February 12, 1852 letter from Spencer Fullerton Baird, Assistant Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution, reveals their collaboration on an annotated list of insect species. Baird writes that “I enclose the... list of species with descriptions of those not yet given.... Not knowing the circumstances, dates I very naturally have not given the desired one. You write these yourself or I will do it if you send the data.” With plenty of field experience, garnered in expeditions to the Rocky Mountains and the territory around Lake Superior, LeConte was evidently a resource person even for fellow naturalists. This is apparent from the fact that even Harvard’s renown Louis Agassiz consulted with the younger LeConte on species identifications. In a May 6, 1852 letter Agassiz asks him for information about a species of Georgia cranfinches. He writes to say that “I did not suppose that it would cost me so little trouble to complete my revision of our Cranfinches; but I have quite finished it and would now ask a favor of you to let me know something about the species of Georgia. I do not remember whether it was you or your father, who told me that one of them burrowed into the ground, while the other lives in the open [?] fields. Will you give me [information] about their habits whatever information you can. I have the two species myself in a goodly number sent by Dr. Jones last year, and I find that they are generically quite distinct.”
One of LeConte’s most faithful international correspondents between 1848 and 1863 was Hermann Rudolph Schaum, a Berlin zoology professor and entomologist. Schaum, had traveled to the United States in 1848 and collected specimens in Louisiana and Ohio. Like LeConte, Schaum specialized in Coleoptera and later published a Catalog of European Coleoptera in 1862. The two men frequently exchanged boxes of insect specimens. For example, in a June 5, 1849 letter Schaum says he had just received the box of specimens that LeConte had promised him the previous winter and that he was preparing a box to be sent out on the Bremen steamer of July 12.
The tone and content of Schaum’s letters to LeConte are always warm and personal, and he often encourages his younger American colleague. One example is a September 2, 1861 letter from Schaum (less than a year after the passing of LeConte’s father) during the first year of the Civil War. He says that he longs “to hear that your personal happiness in your marriage is a counterbalance to the grief, which you must feel at the civil war in your country.” The following year, on November 16, 1862, Schaum writes to congratulate LeConte on his appointment as an Army surgeon and medical inspector, a “very honorable position, where you may be able to do immensely good to your countrymen and to set to naught abuses and calumnies.” He also encourages LeConte to keep on publishing his research on north American entomology, since “the knowledge of insects at present can only be improved by elaborate treatises of local Faunas, of which the author has the whole or almost the whole material of his disposition.”
LeConte also maintained an extensive and long-standing correspondence with such noted European entomologists as the Belgian Theodore Lacordaire and the Russian Carl Robert Osten-Sachen.
The American Civil War largely disrupted LeConte’s entomological research, since like many other scientists, he felt called to serve his country. He was appointed a member of the U.S. Sanitary Commission in 1862 and also volunteered to serve as a surgeon and medical inspector in the Army of the Potomac. During the war years 1863-1865, one of LeConte’s most frequent correspondents is John M. Cuyler, a fellow medical inspector, who is most noted for his glowing report on the care of the wounded at the battle of Gettysburg. The letters from Cuyler for the most part discuss inspection policies and “internal” politics. For example, in a December 9, 1863 letter Cuyler agrees with LeConte’s recommendation that “in all large cities, some one or two of our hospitals [should] be used for a certain class of cases”; “gun shot fractures” to one, and “chronic affections of the respective organs... to the hospital under the charge of Dr. DeCosta.” Another 1863 letter discusses the best schedule for hospital visitations by the inspectors. In the earlier letter Cuyler says he hears “there is a good deal of ‘wire pulling’ going on.” Having been unjustly treated earlier, he decides to keep a low profile and simply “to discharge my official duties honestly and faithfully.” This section of John Lawrence LeConte’s papers also contains several reports; one is a March 10, 1864 “Condensed report” of the examination of 400 discharged veterans to assess the severity of their disabilities. In another December 1864 report LeConte records the percentage of mortality in the General Hospital of Pennsylvania and makes specific recommendations to improve care. After LeConte was mustered out of the Army on October 31, 1865, he refocused his efforts on building his career as a naturalist and an entomologist. To be sure, even in wartime he had never suspended his scientific endeavors. Throughout the war years he corresponded with Benjamin Dann Walsh (later the First State Entomologist of Illinois) on the identification and classification of insect specimens and with George H. Horn, a fellow army surgeon and entomologist stationed in California, who later assisted him with the monograph on weevils and his taxonomy of North American Coleoptera. One of the letters from Walsh (February 3, 1862) asks him for any information on “the habits of the B. variegates besides the little Say states.” LeConte also answered scholarly queries, such as the March 26, 1862 request of New York botanist John Torrey to identify the beetle larva responsible for destroying numerous Austrian Pines in Central Park. He even found time for conferences, attending meetings as a charter member of the National Academy of Sciences in 1863. But about a week after LeConte’s discharge, Smithsonian director Joseph Henry wrote on November 6, 1865 that “we were much pleased to learn that you intended to commence the completion of your work on American Coleoptera." One and a half years later he accepted the proposal of W.W. Wright, Chief Engineer of the Union Pacific Railway, to join the railroad’s survey team as a naturalist together with Assistant geologist C.C. Parry. (March 14, 1867).
Although not all of LeConte’s later endeavors succeeded, his scientific stature increased in the period after the war until his death in 1883. One marker was membership on the Thomson Committee (chaired by Asa Gray) of the new American Association for the Advancement of Science (February 21, 1874). Letters from James Hall (August 10, 1874) and James Dana (August 14, 1874) congratulate him as president-elect of the prestigious new body later that year. A major disappointment for LeConte was his failed candidacy for the office of Commissioner of Agriculture under Republican President Rutherford B. Hayes in 1877. Letters of recommendations supporting LeConte poured into Washington from prominent Philadelphians, such as the editor of the Philadelphia Inquirer (March 15, 1877) and the President of the Franklin Institute (March 1877). He also had the support of the President and senior faculty of the University of East Tennessee (March 30, 1877), and a recommendation from his old army colleague, Colonel John M. Cuyler, by then the U.S. Army’s Medical Director of the Division of the Atlantic (March 12, 1877). The campaign was a failure, although LeConte was later appointed Chief Clerk of the U.S. Mint.
Naval History Note
The LeConte Papers contain several items which may be of interest to naval historians:
Maury, Matthew Fontaine, 1806-1873.
Gould, Benjamin Apthorp. Letter to John L. LeConte. 1857 February 13. Cannot get an ocean map, even from Matthew Fontaine Maury. 2 pages.
Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1877. United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842).
LeConte, John L. Letter to Charles Wilkes. 1847 March 7. Concerning identification of insects collected on the United States Exploring Expedition. 3 pages.
LeConte, John L. Agreement with Charles Wilkes to identify coleoptera found on exploring expedition. 1847 March 25. Manuscript relating to the United States Exploring Expedition. 1 page.
LeConte, John L. Letter to Charles Wilkes. 1847 March 31. Concerning identification of coleoptera collected on the United States Exploring Expedition. 3 pages.
LeConte, John L. Letter to Charles Wilkes. 1847 April 28. Needs certain publications to catalog coleoptra found on the United States Exploring Expedition. 2 pages.
Wilkes, Charles. Letter to John LeConte. 1847 May 9. Concerning books he needs for identification of coleoptera from the United States Exploring, and drawings and engravings for publication. 2 pages.
LeConte, John L. Letter to Charles Wilkes. 1847 June 16. Asks for books from Library of Congress to help him in identifying coleoptera collected on the United States Exploring Expedition. 2 pages.
Torrey, John. Letter to John LeConte. 1849 April 9. Concerning Charles Wilkes' treatment of scientists and his disagreement with him. Can do botany of certain areas of the United States Exploring Expedition, but certainly not all the items Wilkes expects. 3 pages.
Bache, Alexander Dallas. Letter to to John LeConte. 1852 January 2. Will keep after Henry and Wilkes to get the business done. Related to the United States Exploring Expedition. 1 page.
Baird, Spencer Fullerton. Letter to John L. LeConte. 1852 January 19. Entomological specimens. Smithsonian news. Refers to Hademan, Henry, and to Wilkes' exploring expedition. 2 pages.
Early American History Note